Hi, everyone.
My name is Diana Toda.
I'm a DevRel engineer at
VictoriaMetrics, and I'm very happy
to be here at Conf42 Observability.
Today, I'm gonna be presenting
you a talk about how to build your
own green observability pipeline.
So let's get to it.
First of all, some introductions.
Like I said, I'm leading the DevRel
engineering at VictoriaMetrics.
I'm also part of the CNCF community
and OpenTelemetry community as well.
You can get in touch with me
via a bunch of social platforms.
You have the QR code if you wanna scan.
You could always give me a ping, ask me
questions about this presentation and
other topics that I'm handling So my
motivation behind this talk basically
came across randomly in the sense
that I participated a couple of months
ago at a conference, and I saw a very
interesting talk about an open source
project, Green Ops project, called Spruce.
And during this talk, I got thinking
about how I can make more visible this
type of project, if I can embed it and
integrate it with a observability pipeline
with other modern observability tooling.
So then I decided to fiddle with
the project and integrate it with an
observability back-end and front-end.
So simply put, my motivation behind
this was purely curiosity, and then I
came across the idea of why not do it.
So what's the overall
context around this talk?
As many of you probably know or many
of you stumble across this cost and
sustainability data often live in reports,
not necessarily in engineering workflows.
What we normally see is that
observability always has an
environmental footprint, right?
Whether it's from collecting, whether
it's from processing, whether it's
from storing and querying telemetry.
So everything has that
environmental footprint, consumes
energy, carbon, et cetera.
And while we are very eager or
we are very tempted to collect
more data doesn't necessarily
mean better observability, right?
If we are, like, pro- good engineers and
we want to keep our workflows efficient
and we want to reduce the environmental
footprint, we also should think about
reducing the data hoarding, right?
So that means rethinking unnecessary
metrics, excessive cardinality log re- log
retention, and unused telemetry, right?
So there are just a few there are a few
techniques that you can do about that.
If you want to learn more about
the context around this I wrote
an article on a few months ago.
You can scan the QR code.
You also will have it in the resources.
So it's a great read if you are new to
observability or the current setting
when observability is becoming a bit more
excessive and how we can solve this issue.
So the pure objective, practical
objective with my talk is that the
logic is cloud c-cost is telemetry.
Sustainability al- actually is also
telemetry, and we should be able to build
viable green observability pipelines and
observe our GreenOps data as developers.
So there you go.
The next point would be to
actually build this pipeline.
But like I said, first thing,
you can see everything that
I built on the GitHub repo.
You have the URL and also the QR code.
In this open source pipeline,
I'm using Azure Focus reports.
I'll explain everything about that.
Spruce open source project a
Python script, VictoriaMetrics
time-series database Grafana
open source, and Prometheus.
Overall, if we are looking at the
architecture how it's gonna happen,
the overfill, that overflow, that or
workflow that we're gonna see, we're
gonna see that we're gonna access Azure
Focus version one type of reports.
Then we're gonna export it
with the help of Spruce.
We're gonna extract and transform
it into an enriched Parquet file.
And with the help of the script,
basically the Python script that will
export it into Prometheus metrics.
We'll then store it in
VictoriaMetrics time-series database.
We can al- we'll also see the queries
in VictoriaMetrics' user interface, and
also we'll see everything in a Grafana
dashboard that's more elaborated.
So let's get to it.
Why Spruce, first of all?
Like I said, curiosity is one thing
randomness is one thing, but if
we're gonna go and dig deeper around
this project what does it show us?
You can access it on GitHub.
Like I said, it's open source.
And what Bruce Spruce does is bridges
the gap between reading Azure Focus
exports also it's compatible with A-
AWS reports, then it normalizes the
data into Focus compatible Parquet
dataset and enriches each billing record
with sustainability-related attributes
derived from open environmental models.
This is very important to understand.
So Spruce was conceived exactly for this
objective, to give us these very rich
attributes related to sustainability.
So if you want to learn more about
what Spruce is doing, you can head
to the GitHub repo and also to its
official documentation So first of
all, this is was my origin, right?
This Spruce project was the origin.
Then I went ahead and wanted to
integrate it with VictoriaMetrics.
And what is VictoriaMetrics?
VictoriaMetrics is an also an
open source project, provides
a lightweight, high-performance
time series database, and is fully
compatible with Prometheus ecosystem.
The advantage of this is that requires
very little operational overhead.
If you are interested about
VictoriaMetrics ecosystem,
you can head to GitHub repo.
You can scan also the QR code and
you can find out more about it.
What I will do in this talk, in
this presentation, I will use the
VictoriaMetrics user interface to
discover metrics, inspect labels,
experiment with PromQL queries, so that's
Prometheus Query Language, explore metric
cardinality, and validate the exported
sustainability metrics To have a bit
more context about VictoriaMetrics, so
in- because like I said, we are around
a very rich ecosystem of observability
solution the same VictoriaMetrics stack
offers observability solutions, so not
only metrics but also logs and traces.
VictoriaMetrics, VictoriaLogs, and
VictorTraces are open source projects,
so you can head to the GitHub repos
and find out more about those.
And also it offers some other solutions
enterprise, cloud, anomaly detection.
It's fully compatible with
Kubernetes and with OpenTelemetry.
So if you are excited about this project,
you can also find out more about it.
So let's get back to the
pipeline that I was discussing.
So first of all, as explained also in
my GitHub repo, what we'll do at the
beginning, you will set up for example,
either a AWS or an Azure account and then
you'll head out to the cost management
and actually create some exports from
some reports that you're gonna need
because they are compatible with Spruce,
and you need that to actually extract
the data that we're gonna use it later.
So in this case, I extracted
it in couple of formats.
The format that we'll focus on right
now is the version one dot zero,
because it's the newest one at the time
of when I created this GitHub repo.
So what we'll do we'll create the
these reports, and we're gonna
download the generated focus.csv
into exports dash costs reports.
Anyway, once you're gonna be there
you're gonna do the following.
You want to normalize and enrich
with Spruce open source project.
So what will gonna happen, you're gonna
execute Spruce against the generated
input file, so against the CSV file.
What Spru- Spruce is doing is producing
a normalized parquet dataset similar to
this result that you see on the screen,
so exports, cost reports, result focus.
So the dataset now contains both
billing information and environmental
enrichment produced by Spruce.
And we're gonna go ahead
into the s- third step.
The, that, that is let's say
an interesting part when we
convert the data into metrics.
Here I used Python script.
You'll find it in the GitHub repo.
I'm not gonna go into it
because it does the conversion.
What is important for you to understand
is that you'll need to install and run
VictoriaMetrics open the VictoriaMetrics
user inters- interface, and then
export these Prometheus metrics
with the help of the Python script.
Once we are there, obviously, what
the metrics will do will be stored
into VictoriaMetrics' database.
And what we wanna do, obviously, logically
afterwards, is to query our data, right?
So we'll query it in two ways.
We'll look at it via VictoriaMetrics
user interface and also Grafana.
For Grafana, obviously, you'll need to
install and run Grafana open source,
configure the Prometheus data source.
And then for the second part, for the
visualization, you also have in my GitHub
repo, it's a Grafana dashboard that
uses specific carbon-related metrics So
this is the part that is interesting for
this talk because we are focusing right
now on let's say not so used metrics.
So unless you're very deep into
FinOps or GreenOps, you're probably
not gonna u- use this type of
metrics, or you're not gonna be very
familiar with this type of metrics.
So we're gonna spend a bit of
time here going through them.
Luckily Spruce offers already
some metrics it's… in, in
its GitHub repo, in its origin.
Spruce has already a dashboard that is
prepared, but obviously what we want to
do, what I wanted to do with my project is
connect it to more familiar observability
backend and front end, right?
Like I said, the good part is that
some of these metrics that they're
already within Spruce projects.
So it's very good that we have this
already rich sustainability metrics,
and right now we can look a bit
what they're, they are doing, right?
Typical label here, what we'll
have will include the provider, the
service, category resource, region,
SKU, resource name, et cetera.
So if we look at the first metric
name, we'll see cloud cost.
So everything relates to cloud because
obviously it operates with Azure or
AWS, so it's focused on cloud computing.
So the cloud cost obviously will
lead to having information over the
monetary cost for each billing record.
Then cloud usage quantity will
have resource consumption quantity.
Cloud operational energy kilowatts, its
estimated operational energy consumption.
And then we're gonna have very specific,
let's say, carbon-related metrics.
I'm gonna let you look through those.
It's very important that you can find
some of this information related to
what the carbon emissions are doing.
For example the power usage
effectiveness type of metric is related
to data center or to water usage,
and it's really interesting if you
are focused on GreenOps and FinOps.
It's interesting because we're gonna also
use it with Prometheus labels and with
our, let's say, preferred cloud computing
Next, like I said, we want to view
these in VictoriaMetrics user interface
inside the VictoriaMetrics ecosystem
that bears a bunch of advantages.
For example, we'll take a look at
one of these metric that I just
mentioned before, and we can see
already some information here.
What I did here, this is a
screenshot from VictoriaMetrics
user interface Cardinality Explorer.
With the help of Cardinality
Explorer, actually, you could see a
few interesting things like metric
cardinality, label distribution.
So it's very important if you are
operating with time series database.
So I invite you to use Cardinality
Explorer and also other features here
in the VictoriaMetrics user interface.
So you'll have, for example, Query
Analyzer that you can understand
the query execution and performance.
You have data some alerting as well
that you can pair it up and different
information on the raw queries.
If you want to concatenate a few queries
that I just… sorry, a few metrics
that I just showed you right now,
you can create a more complex query.
And you can view something similar to
this graph, where you can see already
some services some storage accounts,
virtual machines, virtual networks.
So obviously this will populate
depending on the resources that you'll
have in that specific cloud provider.
And it's important because
this will populate also related
to how much you're consuming.
And it's interesting to see, for
example, the cloud operational carbon
emissions and any other information
that we just see previously Right.
This is Invicti Metrics user interface.
Like I said, if you are exploring things
with time series database, I invite
you to go ahead and view exactly what
you can do in each of these features.
If you want, for example,
more rich dashboards, right?
Grafana open source is a very used
familiar tool that we can all use.
And I prepared a demo for you.
So this is the actual demo
of the dashboard that I was
showing you in my GitHub repo.
And it's nice, so it's a nice
visualization in terms of what it can do.
So basically here I put information
related to all these metrics that
I showed you in the previous slide.
And this dashboard, what it does,
it combines financial, operational,
environmental metrics into a single view.
So you could see the Prometheus
metrics there that I've been
using, for example, in the metrics
browser, some by service cloud cost.
You could view, I don't know, operational
energy, operational emissions, top
SKUs basically everything, right?
So you have the financial overview here.
We can view all the costs related to
based on group by region, SKU, et cetera.
Sustainability overview then will be a
different let's say a different aspect
that's uncovering in this dashboard.
Operational energy consumption,
embodied carbon emissions, water
consumption power usage effectiveness
and the other related metrics.
And you're gonna see also resource
inventory, resources by service,
resources by region, et cetera.
So if you want to really visu-
visualize your green observability
pipeline of course you can do that.
And I invite you to go ahead and
fully explore what you can do with it.
Obviously, when building any type of
project, nothing will go perfectly.
So you're always gonna have
a few bumps in the road.
You're gonna have some friction
points or just basically some things
that didn't you didn't anticipate
and then you want to rethink a bit.
So for example, when I first created
my pipeline, when I started with the
project I didn't follow, let's say
the, I didn't go by the book in the
sense that I didn't go to the origin.
I created a data simulator.
So it's, How can I say that?
I I created a script in which I-
the data was created was simulated.
That in the end, what it did, it
added more complexity to my pipeline.
And what I didn't get in return,
what I didn't get was actually the
richness of the Spruce sustainability
metrics that it already contains.
So knowing that in the in the overview,
I know that instead of going for a
more complex solution that probably
will not be as clean and interesting as
the original solution, just basically
keep it, try to keep it simple.
Also my option was for Azure instead
of AWS reports because of some AWS free
tier limitations, but it's up to you.
If you already have everything that
you need in terms of cloud tier,
you can go ahead and explore it.
At the moment, Spruce is
compatible only with AWS and Azure.
And also during my endeavors building
the pipeline, I found out that the
Azure billing report had to type
reports, and only the legacy report
was supported by Spruce at that time.
So- The interesting part afterwards
is that I started working with the
maintainers of the Spruce project.
So I created the bug in Spruce project.
I started communicating
with the maintainer.
It was really nice going back and
forth or trying to make suggestions
to the improvements of the project.
Then the maintainers added the new
support for Zero Focus dot one report,
and they also improved the documentation.
And this was a very nice collaboration
that to be honest, it's really
inspiring when you contribute
to any open source project.
That's the benefits of
doing this type of work.
What I see happening in
the future from my side.
So definitely my project doesn't end here.
There's so much more can be done and
something that is for me, something
interesting that I want to do.
So besides the current setup that
I'm using with Victor Metrics and
Grafana, I will also want to add
better sustainability analysis, maybe
incremental imports, multi-cloud
support, carbon budgets sustainability
scorecards, team-level carbon reporting.
That would be nice to have.
On the s-side of observability
definitely a few things that can
be added which exist right now.
So for example, recording
rules Victor Metrics alerting.
So Victor Metrics like you've seen in the
previous slide, has alerting available
in Victor Metrics user interface.
Also I definitely link it
potentially with anomaly detection.
Let's see if that's compatible
or if it's something doable.
Carbon anomaly detection, so it
can be cost anomaly detection or
carbon anomaly detection could be
an idea or forecasting cloud speed.
On the side of Kubernetes obviously
right now Kubernetes is a de facto tool.
It would be nice to also deep
dive into the name-namespace level
attribution cluster cost analysis
and see if there is any way to
add Kubernetes carbon attribution.
Not the least I would also want to
see how it integrates with OpenTele-
OpenTelemetry, which right now is a
graduated cloud-native project and has
become a de facto framework for telemetry.
It would be nice, yeah, to
see how GreenOps interacts
directly with OpenTelemetry.
Not the least, add Kepler integration.
Kepler is already an existing
cloud-native project that is actually
focused on Kubernetes, so it's short
for Kubernetes-based efficient power
exporter, and it's a Prometheus exporter
that measures energy consumption in the…
at the container pod, virtual machine,
and process level, and reads the
hardware sensors and attributes
power based on resource utilization.
Whether or not it can be
integrated with the current
pipeline, it remains to be seen.
So obviously, one of my takeaways
here for you would be once you start
with such a project or any type of
project in general, think about a
concrete outcome and a use case, right?
Set a very palpable expectation.
So you want to see this, you want
to use it for this particular case.
Not like me start simple and stick,
if possible, with open source
and cloud-native tools, right?
Like you've seen, it's always
a better developer experience,
it's a better collaboration.
Probably you have also faster feedback,
and let's face it, the community in
general, it's a lot more welcoming.
Obviously, not being a closed proprietary
project, you'll definitely have more
back and forth from the community.
In my case, I use the storage
backend for the data and a
front end for visualization.
Why?
You will always want to scale some
particular point when obviously you
want to get out of the demo level
with your project, probably you
want to scale, you want to so- show
something sustainable that, and
you want to have a storage backend.
And for visualization, for reporting
issues, you also want to have a nice
front end pro- possibly something that
everybody uses or anyway, it's something
that any like developers and not only
developers can definitely identify with.
If stuck, don't panic.
There's always alternatives
that are available.
There's always other solutions, even
though at the beginning probably that this
might not be a good fit, just wait around,
do your research try different tools.
You'll always see something that has been
tested or it's a potential usage for…
use for you.
If not, create something, right?
So that, that can also be that can also
be the challenge and the good side.
Not the least the resources.
So for this, like I said GreenOps
Observability is just a project, a
home project, if you… a home lab
project that I've been building.
But it's…
has been built with open source project.
Like I said, for me, I'm
interested in observability.
We are here at the conference
about observability.
You can definitely create your
GreenOps your green telemet- telemetry
pipeline using this workflow.
If you ha- have any other ideas this
is the great part, you can go ahead
and elaborate or start something new.
You have all the tools that you need.
If you have any questions,
you can ping me.
You can also ping the Victoria
Metrics team if you are
interested in the solutions.
You have their public Slack that you
can join and ask questions for anything
related to this talk and anything else
to… kinda connected to my profile.
You can also ask me questions, and thank
you very much, and I hope to I hope
you… that you'll have a great day
here at Conference 42 Observability.
Take care.